<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>syllabus | Dr. Courtney R. Gibbons</title>
    <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/tag/syllabus/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://crgibbons.github.io/tag/syllabus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>syllabus</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://crgibbons.github.io/images/logo_hu59eb531666db2293e6941038440d3ac1_22599_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>syllabus</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/tag/syllabus/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 325 (Writing Intensive): Modern Algebra</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2025s-math325/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2025s-math325/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spring 2025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-word-algebra&#34;&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;Algebra&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and its mathematical connotation stem from a 9th century
Arabic treatise entitled, &lt;em&gt;The Concise Book on Calculation by Restoration and Compensation&lt;/em&gt;, by al-Kwarizmi. This historical text dealt with finding the roots of a general quadratic polynomial equation, $ax^2+bx+c=0$ for nonzero $a$, by completing the square&amp;mdash;hence &amp;ldquo;restoration&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;compensation.&amp;rdquo; This is where our journey begins. By the end of the course, we&amp;rsquo;ll have an understanding of what tools and techniques &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; (19th and 20th century) algebra brings to bear on polynomials and their roots. This course gets more abstract as the semester progresses, so set good habits early. (See Endotes 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texts&#34;&gt;Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract Algebra: A Concrete Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Redfield (available from the Hamilton College Bookstore; see me if you have difficulty acquiring the book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Companion to Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Bowers-Green, Leader, and Gowers (access the ebook via the Hamilton College library with your Hamilton SSO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://crgibbons.github.io/files/syllabi/325-S2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Topics Schedule Table (tentative; still being updated!)&lt;/a&gt; or the list at the end of the page for the day-to-day topics coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-and-practices&#34;&gt;Skills and Practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this course works as expected, you will become a better mathematician &lt;em&gt;and a better person&lt;/em&gt; as a result of thinking long and hard about knotty problems; this is a skill that will serve you well in the complicated world we live in. You will, with support from your professor and your peers, develop new ways of thinking and a tolerance for being stumped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Intensive:&lt;/strong&gt; We will focus on writing during class, and you will have several revision opportunities on writing assignments and the writing portions of exams. The final paper in the course will allow you to tie together what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned (and what you&amp;rsquo;ve already written in earlier writing assignments) into a mathematical survey paper written for a mathematically literate audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support your progress as a writer of mathematics, I can help you during open hours, and the QSR Center and the Writing Center both have a number of peer tutors who are familiar with mathematical proof writing and $\LaTeX$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; This course supports several of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hamilton.edu/academics/catalogue/educational-goals-and-curriculum/educational-goals&#34; title=&#34;Hamilton&amp;#39;s Educational Goals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s Educational Goals&lt;/a&gt;. Much of the &lt;em&gt;Disciplinary Practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/em&gt; within mathematics comes through the process of solving a problem/proving a proposition and then writing it up. In this class, you will refine your proof writing skills and develop new mathematical prose writing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-assessments&#34;&gt;Types of Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ready for Class (RC)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Beginning of Class&lt;/em&gt;. We we are working toward answering one (huge!) mathematical problem; you will find it really helpful to review your notes and preview the book for these short quiz-like multiple choice assignments. I don’t reschedule these, but I do drop (at least) three low scores for everyone. For these assessments, you will need a Plickers card (distributed in class). If you lose yours, can you find a printable card here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://crgibbons.github.io/files/PlickersCards_1-40.zip&#34;&gt;Plickers Cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework (HW)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Tuesdays at 4pm (rigid)&lt;/em&gt;. The homework is graded by a Hamilton student and will be returned in 2-3 class periods. Because the written homework is graded by a student who is super-busy just like you, homework is due when it&amp;rsquo;s due! (Don&amp;rsquo;t @ me!) However, to help you out, I drop your lowest 2 homework scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Midterm Exams (ME)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Two 2-hour self-scheduled midterms&lt;/em&gt;. Before the first exam, I will post a preview that describes the kinds of questions, the point distributions, and other information that will help you study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Exam (FE)&lt;/strong&gt;: One 3-hour self-scheduled exam. The material on the final, though cumulative, will be weighted toward the material covered at the end of the course that was not tested on midterms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Assignments (WA)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Thursdays at 4pm (flexible)&lt;/em&gt;. You will write up solutions to problems and responses to writing prompts roughly once a week using $\LaTeX$ (via 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; with your Hamilton credentials) (sometimes solo, sometimes in partners). Each writing assignment is graded among the options &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; (exemplary), &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; (proficient), &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; (revisions necessary to meet expectations), and &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; (not enough to assess). You will have revision opportunities by invitation throughout the semester.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Paper (FP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due by beginning of our scheduled final exam period&lt;/em&gt;. This will be graded like a writing assignment; a lot of the content of this paper will come from writing assignments you&amp;rsquo;ve already completed, so think of it as a way to study for the final and get a chance to revise your writing one last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grades&#34;&gt;Grades&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your base grade (A, B, C, D, or F) is calcullated by a combination of &lt;strong&gt;weighted average&lt;/strong&gt; on some of your assignments (HW (25%); ME and
FE (75%)) and &lt;strong&gt;minimum specifications&lt;/strong&gt; on others (average RC score, scores out of $n$ total writing assignments, and score on the final paper). The following table lists minimum thresholds for each base grade. &lt;strong&gt;You must meet all the requirements in the row to earn that base grade.&lt;/strong&gt; Ranges for $\pm$ will be determined at the end of the semester at the professor’s discretion (typically $-$ will be assigned if you are close to a base grade but didn’t quite meet one of the criteria, and $+$ will be assigned for work consistently at the top of the base grade range).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Base Grade&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ready for Class&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Weighted Avg of HW and Exams&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Writing Assignment scores&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Final Paper score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[90,100)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-2$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; or better and at least 3 &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[80,90)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-3$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; or better and at least 2 &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[70,80)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-3$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[55,70)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-4$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[0,55)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big picture is that, to do well in the course, you will need to demonstrate that you can do the computations well and write well at the 300-level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classroom-environment&#34;&gt;Classroom Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Mathematical Society (the largest professional society for mathematicians) outlines its vision for a welcoming environment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMS strives to ensure that participants in its activities enjoy a welcoming environment. In all its activities, the AMS seeks to foster an atmosphere that encourages the free expression and exchange of ideas. The AMS supports equality of opportunity and treatment for all participants, regardless of gender, gender identity or expression, race, color, national or ethnic origin, religion or religious belief, age, marital status, sexual orientation, disabilities, veteran status, or immigration status&amp;hellip;. A commitment to a welcoming environment is expected of all attendees at AMS activities, including mathematicians, students, guests, staff, contractors and exhibitors, and participants in scientific sessions and social events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am committed to the same vision for our classroom environment, and I sincerely thank you for your contributions toward making our classroom (and office hours) a lively and respectful community of thinkers. Please let me know if you feel that we have strayed from this vision at any point during the semester. (See Endnotes 2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Your Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodations, Conflicts, &amp;amp; Makeup Exams&lt;/strong&gt; Please give me notice at least one week prior to an that you have an academic accommodation or a conflict. Since the exams in this course are self-scheduled, I hope this allows you the flexibility to plan around your other obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy to work with you if you need additional flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendance &amp;amp; Honor&lt;/strong&gt; By enrolling in this class, you are agreeing to be an engaged student, to come to class with a learner&amp;rsquo;s attitude, and to encourage your fellow students to do the same. If you will miss a class, please fill out the Class Absence Request Form (link available on Blackboard). You are part of a community that believes in the power of the Honor Code to make Hamilton College a great place to be a student and a teacher. We are all bound by the responsibility to actively create and maintain a culture of learning, academic integrity, and personal honor. I do not take my responsibility lightly; nor should you! (See Endnotes 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsible Generative AI Use&lt;/strong&gt; You may use generative AI to help you debug $\LaTeX$ errors or assist with tricky formatting (like diagrams or tables). The line you may not cross is this one: &lt;em&gt;You may not use AI&amp;mdash;or any other resource, including calculators, people, solutions manuals, etc.&amp;mdash;to circumvent the thinking and problem-solving you are doing in order to learn the course material.&lt;/em&gt; Any resource that you do use should be cited (format is not terribly important in this class), and if you do use generative AI, you should (a) look for an opensource model and (b) digitally document and submit the prompts and responses from your session. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of an open source AI assistant that&amp;rsquo;s fair game for LaTeX help: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hf.co/chat/assistant/677eb34def23bbff08404623&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Natural Language to LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Stuck&lt;/strong&gt; Being stumped is part of learning mathematics, so please attempt to solve homework problems on your own before asking for help on them. Collaboration on the homework is encouraged as long as you are collaborating with your peers currently enrolled in any section of Math 325. However, make sure to write up your final drafts separately to ensure that you have each fully understood the answer(s). Similarly, even though you will be assigned a writing partner for the writing assignments, it is your responsibility to make sure you understand and approve of all the mathematics your team turns in. (See Endnotes 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;If in doubt, check with me before using resources other than your classmates, tutors at the QSR or Writing Centers, or online $\LaTeX$ help. For example, check with me before asking other professors, students not currently enrolled in Math 325, the internet, a magic eight ball, the ghost of Gauss, etc! Mathematical plagiarism is a subtle business, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to accidentally plagiarize by copying a solution you&amp;rsquo;ve read somewhere else.&lt;/em&gt; (See Endnotes 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Oxford English Dictionary, retrieved 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS Policy on a Welcoming Environment, retrieve 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you wantonly skip class, aside from missing out on the learning community within the walls of our classroom, you&amp;rsquo;ll penalize yourself by getting lower homework and test scores than you otherwise would. And anyway, I do notice if you&amp;rsquo;re not in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor Code issues aside, you&amp;rsquo;re doing your education a disservice if you turn in work you have not personally thought through carefully. Plus, some Writing Assignment problems will reappear on exams or on the final paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, though: you can&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;unsee&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution. There are deep and interesting ethical conundra lurking here; Googling unwisely (or at all) may lead you down a path you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to  low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spring-2025-tentative-schedule-of-topics-may-be-revised-as-we-go&#34;&gt;Spring 2025 Tentative Schedule of Topics (may be revised as we go)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;spring-modern-topics-schedule-2025&#34;&gt;Spring Modern Topics Schedule 2025&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Gibbons will be out of town on days marked with * and will provide instructions for those class periods (some will be synchronous on Zoom, some will be asynchronous videos).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MIDTERM EXAM 1 covers material from chapters 1-8. MIDTERM EXAM 2 coaver material from chapters 9-18. FINAL EXAM covers material from chapters 19-28.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Dates&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Week&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Monday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tuesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Wednesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Thursday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Friday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;01/20/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MLK Jr. Day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;math autobio due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Intro, Chapter 1 (Well-Ordering, Division Algorithm)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 0 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 1 (GCD, FTA)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;01/27/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 1 (Induction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 1 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 3 (Complex Numbers)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 1 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 3 (Complex Numbers)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/03/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 4 (Modular Arithmetic)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 2 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LaTeX, catch-up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 2 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 4 (Zero Divisors, Quats)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/10/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 5 (Fields)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 3 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 5 (Subfields)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 3 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 6 (Solvability by Radicals)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/17/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 6 (Solvability by Radicals)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 4 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7 (Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 4 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7 (Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/24/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7 (Rings)*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 5 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 8 (Polynomial Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 5 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 8 (Polynomial Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/03/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 9 (PIDs)*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 6 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 9 (PIDs)*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;EXAM 1 (Ch 1-8)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ring Homomorphisms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/10/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 10 (Algebraic Elements)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 7 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 10 (Algebraic Elements)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Final Paper Early Draft due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 11 (Irreducibility)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/17/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spring Break&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/31/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 12 (Extension Fields as Vector Spaces)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 7 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 13 (Auts of Fields)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 6 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 14 (Counting Auts)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/07/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 15 (Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WELLNESS DAY (no HW due)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 15 (Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 7 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 16 (Permutation Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/14/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 17 (Group Homomorphisms)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 8 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 18 (Subgroups)*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 8 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 19 (Generators)*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/21/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 20 (Cosets)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 9 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 21 (Lagrange)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;EXAM 2 (Ch 9-18)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 23 (Normal Subgroups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/28/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 23 (Quotient Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 10 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 25 (Galois Revisited)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 9 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 26 (Solvable Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;05/05/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 26 (Solvable Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 11 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 27-28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 10 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catch up/Review*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;05/12/2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catch up/Review&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C&amp;amp;C Day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FINAL EXAM (Ch 19-28) and Final Paper due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- - Class 00: Ch 1, Well-Ordering and Division          
- Class 01: Ch 1, Primes and GCDs                 
- Class 02: Ch 1, Induction, FT of arithmetic     
- Class 03: Ch 3, Complex Numbers                 
- Class 04: Ch 3, Complex Numbers                 
- Class 05: Ch 4, Modular Arithmetic              
- Class 06: LaTeX Day                             
- Class 07: Ch 4, Zero Divisors                   
- Class 08: Ch 5, Fields                          
- Class 09: Ch 5, Subfields                       
- Class 10: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals         
- Class 11: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals         
- Class 12: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 13: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 14: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 15: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings                
- Class 16: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings                
- **NOTE**: Midterm 1 covers Chs 1 through 8         
- Class 17: Ch 9, Ideals                          
- Class 18: Ch 9, Principal Ideals and PIDs       
- Class 19: Ring Homomorphisms                    
- Class 20: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements             
- Class 21: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements             
- Class 22: Ch 11, Irreducible polynomials
- Class 23: Ch 12, Extension Fields as Vector Spaces
- Class 24: Ch 13, Automorphism that Fix a Field  
- Class 25: Ch 14, Counting Automorphisms         
- Class 26: Ch 15, Groups                         
- Class 27: Ch 15, Groups                         
- Class 28: Ch 16, Permutation Groups             
- Class 29: Ch 17, Group Homomorphisms            
- Class 30: Ch 18, Subgroups                      
- **NOTE**: Midterm 2 covers Chs 9 through 18    
- Class 31: Ch 19, Generators of (Sub)Groups      
- Class 32: Ch 20, Cosets                         
- Class 33: Ch 20-21, Cosets and Lagrange&#39;s Theorem 
- Class 34: Ch 23, Normal Subgroups               
- Class 35: Ch 23, Quotient Groups                
- Class 36: Ch 25, Galois Theory Revisited       
- Class 37: Ch 26, Solvable Groups                
- Class 38: Ch 26, Solvable Groups                
- Class 39: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together    
- Class 40: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together    
- Class 41: Workshop on Final Papers              
- **NOTE**: Final Exam emphasizes Chs 19-28  --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 325 (Writing Intensive): Modern Algebra</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2024f-math325/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2024f-math325/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Fall 2024 (updates still coming)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-word-algebra&#34;&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;Algebra&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and its mathematical connotation stem from a 9th century
Arabic treatise entitled, &lt;em&gt;The Concise Book on Calculation by Restoration and Compensation&lt;/em&gt;, by al-Kwarizmi. This historical text dealt with finding the roots of a general quadratic polynomial equation, $ax^2+bx+c=0$ for nonzero $a$, by completing the square&amp;mdash;hence &amp;ldquo;restoration&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;compensation.&amp;rdquo; This is where our journey begins. By the end of the course, we&amp;rsquo;ll have an understanding of what tools and techniques &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; (19th and 20th century) algebra brings to bear on polynomials and their roots. This course gets more abstract as the semester progresses, so set good habits early. (See Endotes 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texts&#34;&gt;Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract Algebra: A Concrete Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Redfield (available from the Hamilton College Bookstore; see me if you have difficulty acquiring the book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Companion to Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Bowers-Green, Leader, and Gowers (access the ebook via the Hamilton College library with your Hamilton SSO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://crgibbons.github.io/files/syllabi/325-S2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Topics Schedule Table (tentative; still being updated!)&lt;/a&gt; or the list at the end of the page for the day-to-day topics coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-and-practices&#34;&gt;Skills and Practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Intensive:&lt;/strong&gt; We will focus on writing during class, and you will have several revision opportunities on writing assignments and the writing portions of exams. The final paper in the course will allow you to tie together what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned (and what you&amp;rsquo;ve already written in earlier writing assignments) into a mathematical survey paper written for a mathematically literate audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support your progress as a writer of mathematics, I can help you during open hours, and the QSR Center and the Writing Center both have a number of peer tutors who are familiar with mathematical proof writing and $\LaTeX$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; This course supports several of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hamilton.edu/academics/catalogue/educational-goals-and-curriculum/educational-goals&#34; title=&#34;Hamilton&amp;#39;s Educational Goals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s Educational Goals&lt;/a&gt;. Much of the &lt;em&gt;Disciplinary Practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/em&gt; within mathematics comes through the process of solving a problem/proving a proposition and then writing it up. In this class, you will refine your proof writing skills and develop new mathematical prose writing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-assessments&#34;&gt;Types of Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ready for Class (RC)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Beginning of Class&lt;/em&gt;. We we are working toward answering one (huge!) mathematical problem; you will find it really helpful to review your notes and preview the book for these short quiz-like multiple choice assignments. I don’t reschedule these, but I do drop (at least) three low scores for everyone. For these assessments, you will need a Plickers card (distributed in class). If you lose yours, can you find a printable card here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://crgibbons.github.io/files/PlickersCards_1-40.zip&#34;&gt;Plickers Cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework (HW)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Tuesdays at 4pm (rigid)&lt;/em&gt;. The homework is graded by a Hamilton student and will be returned in 2-3 class periods. Because the written homework is graded by a student who is super-busy just like you, homework is due when it&amp;rsquo;s due! (Don&amp;rsquo;t @ me!) However, to help you out, I drop your lowest 2 homework scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Midterm Exams (ME)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Two 2-hour self-scheduled midterms&lt;/em&gt;. Before the first exam, I will post a preview that describes the kinds of questions, the point distributions, and other information that will help you study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Exam (FE)&lt;/strong&gt;: One 3-hour cumulative self-scheduled exam. The material on the final, though cumulative, will be weighted toward the material covered at the end of the course that was not tested on midterms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Assignments (WA)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Thursdays at 4pm (flexible)&lt;/em&gt;. You will write up solutions to problems and responses to writing prompts roughly once a week using $\LaTeX$ (via 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; with your Hamilton credentials) (sometimes solo, sometimes in partners). Each writing assignment is graded among the options &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; (exemplary), &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; (masterful), &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; (revisions necessary to meet expectations), and &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; (not enough to assess). You will have revision opportunities by invitation throughout the semester.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Paper (FP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due by beginning of our scheduled final exam period&lt;/em&gt;. This will be graded like a writing assignment; a lot of the content of this paper will come from writing assignments you&amp;rsquo;ve already completed, so think of it as a way to study for the final and get a chance to revise your writing one last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grades&#34;&gt;Grades&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your base grade (A, B, C, D, or F) is calcullated by a combination of &lt;strong&gt;weighted average&lt;/strong&gt; on some of your assignments (HW (25%); ME and
FE (75%)) and &lt;strong&gt;minimum specifications&lt;/strong&gt; on others (average RC score, scores out of $n$ total writing assignments, and score on the final paper). The following table lists minimum thresholds for each base grade. &lt;strong&gt;You must meet all the requirements in the row to earn that base grade.&lt;/strong&gt; Ranges for $\pm$ will be determined at the end of the semester at the professor’s discretion (typically $-$ will be assigned if you are close to a base grade but didn’t quite meet one of the criteria, and $+$ will be assigned for work consistently at the top of the base grade range).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Base Grade&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ready for Class&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Weighted Avg of HW and Exams&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Writing Assignment scores&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Final Paper score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[90,100)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-2$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[80,90)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-3$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[70,80)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-2$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[55,70)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n-4$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[0,55)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$n$ scores of &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; or better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big picture is that, to do well in the course, you will need to demonstrate that you can do the computations well and write well at the 300-level.  Throughout the semester you will have opportunities to revise your writing (and potentially receive a new score on an assignment) by responding to professor feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classroom-environment&#34;&gt;Classroom Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Mathematical Society (the largest professional society for mathematicians) outlines its vision for a welcoming environment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMS strives to ensure that participants in its activities enjoy a welcoming environment. In all its activities, the AMS seeks to foster an atmosphere that encourages the free expression and exchange of ideas. The AMS supports equality of opportunity and treatment for all participants, regardless of gender, gender identity or expression, race, color, national or ethnic origin, religion or religious belief, age, marital status, sexual orientation, disabilities, veteran status, or immigration status&amp;hellip;. A commitment to a welcoming environment is expected of all attendees at AMS activities, including mathematicians, students, guests, staff, contractors and exhibitors, and participants in scientific sessions and social events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am committed to the same vision for our classroom environment, and I sincerely thank you for your contributions toward making our classroom (and office hours) a lively and respectful community of thinkers. Please let me know if you feel that we have strayed from this vision at any point during the semester. (See Endnotes 2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Your Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodations, Conflicts, &amp;amp; Makeup Exams&lt;/strong&gt; Please give me notice at least one week prior to an that you have an academic accommodation or a conflict. Since the exams in this course are self-scheduled, I hope this allows you the flexibility to plan around your other obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy to work with you if you need additional flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendance &amp;amp; Honor&lt;/strong&gt; By enrolling in this class, you are agreeing to be an engaged student, to come to class with a learner&amp;rsquo;s attitude, and to encourage your fellow students to do the same. If you need to miss a class, please fill out the Class Absence Request Form (link available on Blackboard). You are part of a community that believes in the power of the Honor Code to make Hamilton College a great place to be a student and a teacher. We are all bound by the responsibility to actively create and maintain a culture of learning, academic integrity, and personal honor. I do not take my responsibility lightly; nor should you! (See Endnotes 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Stuck&lt;/strong&gt; Being stumped is part of learning mathematics, so please attempt to solve homework problems on your own before asking for help on them. Collaboration on the homework is encouraged as long as you are collaborating with your peers currently enrolled in any section of Math 325. However, make sure to write up your final drafts separately to ensure that you have each fully understood the answer(s). Similarly, even though you will be assigned a writing partner for the writing assignments, it is your responsibility to make sure you understand and approve of all the mathematics your team turns in. (See Endnotes 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Please check with me before using resources other than your classmates, tutors at the QSR or Writing Centers, or online $\LaTeX$ help. For example, check with me before asking other professors, students not currently enrolled in Math 325, the internet, a magic eight ball, the ghost of Gauss, etc! Mathematical plagiarism is a subtle business, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to accidentally plagiarize by copying a solution you&amp;rsquo;ve read somewhere else.&lt;/em&gt; (See Endnotes 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Oxford English Dictionary, retrieved 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS Policy on a Welcoming Environment, retrieve 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you wantonly skip class, aside from missing out on the learning community within the walls of our classroom, you&amp;rsquo;ll penalize yourself by getting lower homework and test scores than you otherwise would. And anyway, I do notice if you&amp;rsquo;re not in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor Code issues aside, you&amp;rsquo;re doing your education a disservice if you turn in work you have not personally thought through carefully. Plus, some Writing Assignment problems will reappear on exams or on the final paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, though: you can&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;unsee&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution. There are deep and interesting ethical conundra lurking here; Googling unwisely (or at all) may lead you down a path you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to  low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fall-2024-schedule-of-topics-may-be-revised&#34;&gt;Fall 2024 Schedule of Topics (may be revised)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Monday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tuesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Wednesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Thursday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Friday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8/30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Introductions &lt;br&gt; The Quadratic Formula&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 1 &lt;br&gt; (Divisibility)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 1 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 1 &lt;br&gt; (FTa, Induction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 1 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 3 &lt;br&gt; (Complex Nums)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 3 &lt;br&gt; (Complex Nums)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 2 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LaTeX Day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 2 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 4 &lt;br&gt; (Modulo N)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 4 &lt;br&gt; (Zero Divs, Quats)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 3 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 5 &lt;br&gt; (Fields &amp;amp; Subfields)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 3 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 5/6 &lt;br&gt; (Solv by Rads)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 6 &lt;br&gt; (Solvable by Rads)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 4 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7 &lt;br&gt; (Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 4 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7 &lt;br&gt; (Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9/30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 7/8 &lt;br&gt; (Poly. Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 5 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 8 &lt;br&gt; (Polynomial Rings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA Rewrite due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 9 &lt;br&gt; (PIDs)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 9 &lt;br&gt; (PIDs)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 6 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ring Homomorphisms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Midterm 1 &lt;br&gt; (self-scheduled)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 11 &lt;br&gt; (Irreducibility)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 10 &lt;br&gt; (Algebraic Elts)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 7 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 10 &lt;br&gt; (Algebraic Elts)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 5 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 12 &lt;br&gt; (Fields as VS)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 8 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 13 &lt;br&gt; (Auts of Fields)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 6 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 14 &lt;br&gt; (Counting Auts)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 15 &lt;br&gt; (Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 9 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 15 &lt;br&gt; (Groups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 7 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 16 &lt;br&gt; (Permutations)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 17 &lt;br&gt; (Group Homoms)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 10 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 18 &lt;br&gt; (Subgroups)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Midterm 2 &lt;br&gt; (self-scheduled)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 19 &lt;br&gt; (Generators)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 20 &lt;br&gt; (Cosets)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 11 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 21 &lt;br&gt; (Lagrange)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 8 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 23 &lt;br&gt; (Normal Sgps)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 23 &lt;br&gt; (Quotient Gps)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 12 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 25 &lt;br&gt; (Galois again)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 9 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thanksgiving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 26 &lt;br&gt; (Solvable Gps)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 13 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 26 &lt;br&gt; (Commutators)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 10 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapter 26 &lt;br&gt; (Commutators)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chapters 27-28 &lt;br&gt; (Putting it Together)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HW 14 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catch-up/Review&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA 11 due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catch-up/Review&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- - Class 00: Ch 1, Well-Ordering and Division          
- Class 01: Ch 1, Primes and GCDs                 
- Class 02: Ch 1, Induction, FT of arithmetic     
- Class 03: Ch 3, Complex Numbers                 
- Class 04: Ch 3, Complex Numbers                 
- Class 05: Ch 4, Modular Arithmetic              
- Class 06: LaTeX Day                             
- Class 07: Ch 4, Zero Divisors                   
- Class 08: Ch 5, Fields                          
- Class 09: Ch 5, Subfields                       
- Class 10: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals         
- Class 11: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals         
- Class 12: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 13: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 14: Ch 7, Rings                           
- Class 15: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings                
- Class 16: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings                
- **NOTE**: Midterm 1 covers Chs 1 through 8         
- Class 17: Ch 9, Ideals                          
- Class 18: Ch 9, Principal Ideals and PIDs       
- Class 19: Ring Homomorphisms                    
- Class 20: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements             
- Class 21: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements             
- Class 22: Ch 11, Irreducible polynomials
- Class 23: Ch 12, Extension Fields as Vector Spaces
- Class 24: Ch 13, Automorphism that Fix a Field  
- Class 25: Ch 14, Counting Automorphisms         
- Class 26: Ch 15, Groups                         
- Class 27: Ch 15, Groups                         
- Class 28: Ch 16, Permutation Groups             
- Class 29: Ch 17, Group Homomorphisms            
- Class 30: Ch 18, Subgroups                      
- **NOTE**: Midterm 2 covers Chs 9 through 18    
- Class 31: Ch 19, Generators of (Sub)Groups      
- Class 32: Ch 20, Cosets                         
- Class 33: Ch 20-21, Cosets and Lagrange&#39;s Theorem 
- Class 34: Ch 23, Normal Subgroups               
- Class 35: Ch 23, Quotient Groups                
- Class 36: Ch 25, Galois Theory Revisited       
- Class 37: Ch 26, Solvable Groups                
- Class 38: Ch 26, Solvable Groups                
- Class 39: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together    
- Class 40: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together    
- Class 41: Workshop on Final Papers              
- **NOTE**: Final Exam emphasizes Chs 19-28  --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 512: Number Theory</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2024-math512/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2024-math512/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Fall 2024&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;number-theorists-are-like-lotus-eaters----having-tasted-this-food-they-can-never-give-it-up--leopold-kronecker&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Number Theorists are like lotus eaters -  having tasted this food they can never give it up.&amp;rdquo; -Leopold Kronecker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s up with prime numbers?&amp;rdquo; is our motivating question for a lot of this course. &amp;ldquo;How can we use that cool property of prime numbers?&amp;rdquo; is our motivating question for most of the rest. Number theory begins with the integers and the relationships (and remainders) that come from trying to divide one integer into another or find integer solutions to polynomial equations (like $x^3 + y^3 + z^3 = 42$). Although some original numberphiles celebrated number theory&amp;rsquo;s purity (read: its lack of applications to the &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo;), they&amp;rsquo;d be annoyed to know that we now use their results to accomplish many practical ends, like sending information via secure webpages, listening to scratched CDs, and speed-testing computers. This course will focus on the fundamental results in the field and their applications (especially to cryptography and cryptanalysis). Expect distinguished visitors from different schools and sectors to give short guest presentations in class. (See Endnotes 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texts&#34;&gt;Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookstore.ams.org/view?ProductCode=TEXT/9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Number Theory Through Inquiry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by David C. Marshall, Edward Odell, and Michael Starbird (available from the Hamilton College Bookstore; see me if you have difficulty acquiring the book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Companion to Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Bowers-Green, Leader, and Gowers (access the ebook via the Hamilton College library with your Hamilton SSO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students will be (collectively) responsible for preparing, presenting, and recording solutions to almost every problem in Chapters 1-6. This makes it difficult to predict exactly when each topic will be covered, but we&amp;rsquo;ll start by assuming the following breakdown (roughly) and adapting as necessary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First third of the semester: Chapters 1-3;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middle third of the semester: Chapters 4-6;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remaining third of the semester: Choose Your Own Adventure (see below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In defiance of linear time: We will also cover some basic principles of cryptography and cryptanalysis &amp;ldquo;between&amp;rdquo; the first and second thirds of the semester.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-and-practices&#34;&gt;Skills and Practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaking Intensive:&lt;/strong&gt; This class will help you develop your ability to communicate mathematics orally in both formal and informal settings, and you will have several assessments to help you keep track of your progress: two oral midterms of very different natures along with assessments of your class presentations.
To support your progress as an oral communicator of mathematics, I can help you during open hours and the QSR Center and the Oral Communication Center both have peer tutors who are familiar with mathematical presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; This course supports several of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hamilton.edu/academics/catalogue/educational-goals-and-curriculum/educational-goals&#34; title=&#34;Hamilton&amp;#39;s Educational Goals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s Educational Goals&lt;/a&gt;. Much of the &lt;em&gt;Disciplinary Practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/em&gt; within mathematics comes through the process of solving a problem or proving a proposition and communicating it to others. In this class, you will put your proof writing skills to work and develop new mathematical speaking skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active Learning:&lt;/strong&gt; At first, you might feel a little uncomfortable if you are used to lecture-based classes, but there&amp;rsquo;s good news! A 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2019/09/study-shows-that-students-learn-more-when-taking-part-in-classrooms-that-employ-active-learning-strategies/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harvard study&lt;/a&gt; in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences recently demonstrated that students learn more in active learning classes: &amp;ldquo;[T]hough students felt as if they learned more through traditional lectures, they actually learned more when taking part in classrooms that employed so-called active-learning strategies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-assessments&#34;&gt;Types of Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active Attendance and Participation (AAP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Every Class&lt;/em&gt;. (10%) Get ready to work like a mathematician in this class. No more lectures! This class is active learning all-the-way, which means your attendance is critical for its success. You and your classmates will work together and uncover the major results through activities, groupwork, and good, old-fashioned hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class Participation (CP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Frequently&lt;/em&gt;.  (10%) Everyone will present often. Your CP grade will include your presentations and also your active participation in the discussion following (and sometimes during) others&amp;rsquo; presentations. Want help? Visit the Oral Communication Center to practice presenting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oral Midterm Exam (OME)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;30 minutes&lt;/em&gt;. (20%) We will use a random number generator (like a 10-sided die) to select from a list of pre-selected midterm problems, and you will present the selected problem to me in my office at the blackboard. I will follow up with some questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oral Midterm Conversation (OMC)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;30 minutes.&lt;/em&gt; (20%) You will explain an application of Number Theory to a non-specialist during this exam. Details will be posted on Blackboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Midterm Skills Exam (MSE)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;1 hour&lt;/em&gt;. (15%) This short problem set will test your computational skills. Provided the Honor Code is working for our class, you will be able to self-schedule this exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose Your Own Adventure (CYOA)&lt;/strong&gt;: (25%) Team-based self-guided inquiry on a number theoretic topic of your choosing. A menu of options is available, but you can also pitch your own topic. As part of this assignment, you will write a short chapter on the topic in the collaborative course notes (including homework problems and solutions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;grades&#34;&gt;Grades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;A+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;A-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;D+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;D-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;98%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;84%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;77%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;62%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classroom-environment&#34;&gt;Classroom Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Mathematical Society (the largest professional society for mathematicians) outlines its vision for a welcoming environment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMS strives to ensure that participants in its activities enjoy a welcoming environment. In all its activities, the AMS seeks to foster an atmosphere that encourages the free expression and exchange of ideas. The AMS supports equality of opportunity and treatment for all participants, regardless of gender, gender identity or expression, race, color, national or ethnic origin, religion or religious belief, age, marital status, sexual orientation, disabilities, veteran status, or immigration status&amp;hellip;. A commitment to a welcoming environment is expected of all attendees at AMS activities, including mathematicians, students, guests, staff, contractors and exhibitors, and participants in scientific sessions and social events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am committed to the same vision for our classroom environment, and I sincerely thank you for your contributions toward making our classroom (and office hours) a lively and respectful community of thinkers. Please let me know if you feel that we have strayed from this vision at any point during the semester. (See Endnotes 2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Your Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodations, Conflicts, &amp;amp; Makeup Exams.&lt;/strong&gt; Please give me notice at least one week prior to an that you have an academic accommodation or a conflict. Since the exams in this course are self-scheduled, I hope this allows you the flexibility to plan around your other obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy to work with you if you need additional flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendance &amp;amp; Honor.&lt;/strong&gt; By enrolling in this class, you are agreeing to be an engaged student, to come to class with a learner&amp;rsquo;s attitude, and to encourage your fellow students to do the same. If you need to miss a class, please fill out the Class Absence Request Form (link available on Blackboard). You are part of a community that believes in the power of the Honor Code to make Hamilton College a great place to be a student and a teacher. We are all bound by the responsibility to actively create and maintain a culture of learning, academic integrity, and personal honor. I do not take my responsibility lightly; nor should you! (See Endnotes 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Stuck.&lt;/strong&gt; Being stumped is part of learning mathematics, so please attempt to solve problems on your own before asking for help on them. Collaboration on problem sets is encouraged as long as you are collaborating with your peers currently enrolled in any section of Math 512. However, make sure to write up your final drafts separately to ensure that you have each fully understood the answer(s). Similarly, even though you may submit joint assignments, it is your responsibility to make sure you understand and approve of all the mathematics your team turns in. (See Endnotes 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Please check with me before using resources other than your classmates, tutors at the Academic Resource Centers, or online $\LaTeX$ help. For example, check with me before asking other professors, students not currently enrolled in Math 325, the internet, a magic eight ball, the ghost of Gauss, etc! Mathematical plagiarism is a subtle business, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to accidentally plagiarize by copying a solution you&amp;rsquo;ve read somewhere else.  If you use external resources on an assignment that allows them, you must use an open source resource (no Chegg, Math Stack Exchange, or ChatGPT!), you must disclose that you used it, and in the case of generative AI you must share your prompt or sequence of prompts.&lt;/em&gt; (See Endnotes 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oed.com/dictionary/number-theory_n#11162207&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;, retrieved 08/19/2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS Policy on a Welcoming Environment, retrieved 08/19/2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you wantonly skip class, aside from missing out on the learning community within the walls of our classroom, you&amp;rsquo;ll penalize yourself by getting lower homework and test scores than you otherwise would. And anyway, I do notice if you&amp;rsquo;re not in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor Code issues aside, you&amp;rsquo;re doing your education a disservice if you turn in work you have not personally thought through carefully. Plus, some problems will reappear on exams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, though: you can&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;unsee&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution. There are deep and interesting ethical conundra lurking here; Googling or GPTing unwisely (or at all) may lead you down a path you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to follow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 498 (Seminar): Mathematics in Social Context</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2022-math498/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2022-math498/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Spring 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-big-picture&#34;&gt;The Big Picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to examine issues of social, structural, and institutional hierarchies that intersect with mathematics and statistics. This year, the course will examine several big themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Belonging&lt;/strong&gt; – what is “mathematical identity” and where does it come from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Rights&lt;/strong&gt; – can mathematical literacy be viewed as a tool for advancing equity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Districting&lt;/strong&gt; – how does mathematics help us understand gerrymandering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; – in what ways do algorithms contribute to or fight against social stratification?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;educational-goals&#34;&gt;Educational Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to satisfying the Social, Structural, and Institutional Hierarchies (SSIH) requirement for the concentration in Mathematics and Statistics, this course addresses the following Educational Goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intellectual Curiosity and Flexibility&lt;/strong&gt; – examining fact, phenomena, and issues in-depth, and from a variety of perspectives, and having the courage to revise beliefs and outlooks in light of new evidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding of Cultural Diversity&lt;/strong&gt; – critically engaging with multiple cultural traditions and perspectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethical, Informed, and Engaged Citizenship&lt;/strong&gt; – developing an awareness of the challenges and responsibilities of local, national, and global citizenship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/strong&gt; – expressing oneself with clarity and eloquence, in both traditional and contemporary media, through writing and speaking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expectations-and-assignments&#34;&gt;Expectations and Assignments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To dig deeply into the main themes of the course, you will need to prepare in advance for each class, actively participate, and complete all of the assignments. This is reflected in the final grade composition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog Posts: 40%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participation: 30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final Poster: 30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-class-tasks-reading-watching-or-listening&#34;&gt;Pre-Class Tasks (Reading, Watching, or Listening)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete the relevant task (reading, watching, or listening) assigned for each class, think about it carefully, and outline some thoughts to share in our class discussion. The list of tasks can be found on the last page of this document and may be updated (in a timely manner!) as the semester progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your attendance and active participation is really important to the stability and success of our learning community! If you need to miss more classes, please fill out the Absence Request Form in advance (link available on Blackboard). Every student may miss one class; if you need to miss more than that, we need to talk. Undiscussed absences (besides the first freebie) will lower your participation grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;blog-posts&#34;&gt;Blog Posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our course blog is a (class-only) space for you to engage critically with the course materials. Writing the blog posts will help you and your classmates initiate and inform class discussions. They will also give you the opportunity to practice skills directly related to effective writing, such as conciseness, clarity, and vividness. You will contribute an original blog post five (5) times throughout the semester according to the schedule posted on Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each blog post should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify a specific concept/idea/argument from the assigned task (with reference);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;either demonstrate understanding of the concept at issue and express agreement or disagreement, giving reasons, OR connect it to previous ideas/discussions, or to contemporary issues, OR introduce an example/counter-example not explored in the text;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be more than be simply a summary or an unsupported opinion (“I liked this reading”);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end with a potential question or topic for class discussion, related to your post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each blog post should be between 150 and 250 words. You must post your contribution by 7pm the day before our class meeting. I will grade each post according to the rubric posted on Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-poster&#34;&gt;Final Poster&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a capstone assignment, you will create a poster to explore a topic of your choice. This poster will be due after spring break, and we will convene for one more class session to present the class posters to the Math and Stats department.  You must submit a brief outline (bullet points are fine) of the content of your poster by the last day of the course. A pdf of your final poster is the third Tuesday after spring break, and you should submit your request to print the poster to LITS on this date as well. The poster should be well organized with clear exposition and proper citations. Please see &lt;a href=&#34;https://libguides.hamilton.edu/c.php?g=749942&amp;amp;p=5370642&#34;&gt;https://libguides.hamilton.edu/c.php?g=749942&amp;amp;p=5370642&lt;/a&gt; for more information about the technical aspects of creating a poster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;required-books&#34;&gt;Required Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations: Civil Rights from Mississippi to the Algebra Project (Beacon Press, 2001)
NOTE: ebook available with Hamilton College login
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hamilton.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01HAMILTON_INST/15ojthq/alma9917657883304131&#34;&gt;https://hamilton.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01HAMILTON_INST/15ojthq/alma9917657883304131&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor-code&#34;&gt;Honor Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your blog posts and final poster must consist primarily of your own individual work and include citations for works that you are responding to or works that informed your thinking (this includes formal works, websites, videos, or other sources). You and I are also bound by the Hamilton Honor Code to report instances of plagiarism or other academic dishonesty that we become aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accessibility&#34;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students who require academic accommodations should contact the Dean of Students Office to coordinate services. Talk to me to ensure that your needs will be met this semester, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading-and-discussion-schedule&#34;&gt;Reading and Discussion Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-1---belonging&#34;&gt;Week 1 - Belonging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introductions, Classroom Conversations, and Mathematics Identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-2-and-3---civil-rights&#34;&gt;Weeks 2 and 3 - Civil Rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Andrew Hacker, Is Algebra Really Necessary?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Radical Equations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations, Chapters 1 and 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Radical Equations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations, Chapters 3 and 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - College Rankings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-4-5-and-6---political-districting&#34;&gt;Weeks 4, 5, and 6 - Political Districting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Gerrymandering Overview&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: David Wasserman, “Hating Gerrymandering is Easy: Fixing it is Harder” FiveThirtyEight, The Gerrymandering Project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read:  Nick Corasanti et al., “How Maps Reshape American Politics”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Efficiency Gap&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Mira Bernstein and Moon Duchin, A Formula Goes to Court: Partisan Gerrymandering and the Efficiency Gap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Monte Carlo Markov Chains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday- Supreme Court&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Elena Kagan, Opinion and Dissent in Gerrymandering Case, June 27, 2019
&lt;em&gt;This document is 72 pages long; allow 2 - 3 hours reading time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, Trial by Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Laurence Tribe, Trial by Mathematics: Precision and Ritual in the Legal Process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-6-and-7---algorithms&#34;&gt;Weeks 6 and 7 - Algorithms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Cathy O’Neill, Weapons of Math Destruction, Intro &amp;amp; Chapters 1, 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Ethical Applications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch: Youtube Playlist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - The Ethics Matrix&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Cathy O’Neil and Hanna Gunn, “The Ethical Matrix” [Introduction, Sections 8.4-8.7]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-8---belonging-revisited&#34;&gt;Week 8 - Belonging Revisited&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Belonging Revisited&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: “STEM Identity Development in Latinas: The Role of Self- and Outside Recognition” [Section - Literature Review (pp. 2-3); Section - Implications for Policy and Practice (pp. 16-17)]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen: My Favorite Theorem podcast interview with Ranthony Edmonds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday- Course Conclusions&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 325 (Writing Intensive): Modern Algebra</title>
      <link>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2022-math325/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://crgibbons.github.io/post/syllabi/2022-math325/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Spring 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-word-algebra&#34;&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;Algebra&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and its mathematical connotation stem from a 9th century
Arabic treatise entitled, &lt;em&gt;The Concise Book on Calculation by Restoration and Compensation&lt;/em&gt;, by al-Kwarizmi. This historical text dealt with finding the roots of a general quadratic polynomial equation, $ax^2+bx+c=0$ for nonzero $a$, by completing the square&amp;mdash;hence &amp;ldquo;restoration&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;compensation.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; This is where our journey begins. By the end of the course, we&amp;rsquo;ll have an understanding of what tools and techniques &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; (19th and 20th century) algebra brings to bear on polynomials and their roots. This course gets more abstract as the semester progresses, so set good habits early. (See Endotes 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texts&#34;&gt;Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract Algebra: A Concrete Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Redfield (available from the Hamilton College Bookstore; see me if you have difficulty acquiring the book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Companion to Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Bowers-Green, Leader, and Gowers (access the ebook via the Hamilton College library with your Hamilton SSO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://crgibbons.github.io/files/syllabi/325-S2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Topics Schedule Table (tentative)&lt;/a&gt; or the list at the end of the page for the day-to-day topics coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-and-practices&#34;&gt;Skills and Practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Intensive:&lt;/strong&gt; We will focus on writing during class, and you will have several revision opportunities on writing assignments and the writing portions of exams. The final paper in the course will allow you to tie together what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned (and what you&amp;rsquo;ve already written in earlier writing assignments) into a mathematical survey paper written for a mathematically literate audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support your progress as a writer of mathematics, I can help you during open hours or on Piazza, and the QSR Center and the Writing Center both have a number of peer tutors who are familiar with mathematical proof writing and $\LaTeX$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; This course supports several of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hamilton.edu/academics/catalogue/educational-goals-and-curriculum/educational-goals&#34; title=&#34;Hamilton&amp;#39;s Educational Goals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s Educational Goals&lt;/a&gt;. Much of the &lt;em&gt;Disciplinary Practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/em&gt; within mathematics comes through the process of solving a problem/proving a proposition and then writing it up. In this class, you will refine your proof writing skills and develop new mathematical prose writing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-assessments&#34;&gt;Types of Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ready for Class (RC)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Beginning of Class&lt;/em&gt;. We we are working toward answering one (huge!) mathematical problem; you will find it really helpful to review your notes and preview the book for these short quiz-like multiple choice assignments. I don’t reschedule these, but I do drop (at least) three low scores for everyone. (We can work out COVID contingencies as necessary!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework (HW)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Tuesdays at 4pm (rigid)&lt;/em&gt;. The homework is graded by a Hamilton student and will be returned in 2-3 class periods. Because the written homework is graded by a student who is super-busy just like you, homework is due when it&amp;rsquo;s due! (Don&amp;rsquo;t @ me!) However, to help you out, I drop your lowest 2 homework scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Midterm Exams (ME)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Two 2-hour self-scheduled midterms&lt;/em&gt;. Before the first exam, I will post a preview that describes the kinds of questions, the point distributions, and other information that will help you study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Exam (FE)&lt;/strong&gt;: One 3-hour cumulative self-scheduled exam. The material on the final, though cumulative, will be weighted toward the material covered at the end of the course that was not tested on midterms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Assignments (WA)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Thursdays at 4pm (flexible)&lt;/em&gt;. You will write up solutions to problems and responses to writing prompts roughly once a week using $\LaTeX$ (via 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; with your Hamilton SSO) (sometimes solo, sometimes in partners). Each writing assignment is graded among the options &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; (exemplary), &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; (masterful), &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; (consider revising), and &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; (not enough to assess).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Paper (FP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due by beginning of our scheduled final exam period&lt;/em&gt;. This will be graded like a writing assignment; a lot of the content of this paper will come from writing assignments you&amp;rsquo;ve already completed, so think of it as a way to study for the final and get a chance to revise your writing one last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classroom-environment&#34;&gt;Classroom Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Mathematical Society (the largest professional society for mathematicians) outlines its vision for a welcoming environment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMS strives to ensure that participants in its activities enjoy a welcoming environment. In all its activities, the AMS seeks to foster an atmosphere that encourages the free expression and exchange of ideas. The AMS supports equality of opportunity and treatment for all participants, regardless of gender, gender identity or expression, race, color, national or ethnic origin, religion or religious belief, age, marital status, sexual orientation, disabilities, veteran status, or immigration status&amp;hellip;. A commitment to a welcoming environment is expected of all attendees at AMS activities, including mathematicians, students, guests, staff, contractors and exhibitors, and participants in scientific sessions and social events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am committed to the same vision for our classroom environment, and I sincerely thank you for your contributions toward making our classroom (and office hours) a lively and respectful community of thinkers. Please let me know if you feel that we have strayed from this vision at any point during the semester. (See Endnotes 2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Your Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodations, Conflicts, &amp;amp; Makeup Exams&lt;/strong&gt; Please give me notice at least one week prior to an that you have an academic accommodation or a conflict. Since the exams in this course are self-scheduled, I hope this allows you the flexibility to plan around your other obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy to work with you if you need additional flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendance &amp;amp; Honor&lt;/strong&gt; By enrolling in this class, you are agreeing to be an engaged student, to come to class with a learner&amp;rsquo;s attitude, and to encourage your fellow students to do the same. If you need to miss a class, please fill out the Class Absence Request Form (link available on Blackboard). You are part of a community that believes in the power of the Honor Code to make Hamilton College a great place to be a student and a teacher. We are all bound by the responsibility to actively create and maintain a culture of learning, academic integrity, and personal honor. I do not take my responsibility lightly; nor should you! (See Endnotes 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Stuck&lt;/strong&gt; Being stumped is part of learning mathematics, so please attempt to solve homework problems on your own before asking for help on them. Collaboration on the homework is encouraged as long as you are collaborating with your peers currently enrolled in any section of Math 325. However, make sure to write up your final drafts separately to ensure that you have each fully understood the answer(s). Similarly, even though you will be assigned a writing partner for the writing assignments, it is your responsibility to make sure you understand and approve of all the mathematics your team turns in. (See Endnotes 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Please check with me before using resources other than your classmates, tutors at the QSR or Writing Centers, or online $\LaTeX$ help. For example, check with me before asking other professors, students not currently enrolled in Math 325, the internet, a magic eight ball, the ghost of Gauss, etc! Mathematical plagiarism is a subtle business, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to accidentally plagiarize by copying a solution you&amp;rsquo;ve read somewhere else.&lt;/em&gt; (See Endnotes 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Oxford English Dictionary, retrieved 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS Policy on a Welcoming Environment, retrieve 01/30/2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you wantonly skip class, aside from missing out on the learning community within the walls of our classroom, you&amp;rsquo;ll penalize yourself by getting lower homework and test scores than you otherwise would. And anyway, I do notice if you&amp;rsquo;re not in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor Code issues aside, you&amp;rsquo;re doing your education a disservice if you turn in work you have not personally thought through carefully. Plus, some Writing Assignment problems will reappear on exams or on the final paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, though: you can&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;unsee&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution. There are deep and interesting ethical conundra lurking here; Googling unwisely (or at all) may lead you down a path you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to  low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spring-2022-schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Spring 2022 Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 01/19/2022: Ch 1, Well-Ordering and Division&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 01/21/2022: Ch 1, Primes and GCDs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 01/24/2022: Ch 1, Induction,  FT of arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 01/26/2022: Ch 3, Complex Numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 01/28/2022: Ch 3, Complex Numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 01/31/2022: Ch 4, Modular Arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/02/2022: LaTeX Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/04/2022: Ch 4, Zero Divisors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/07/2022: Ch 5, Fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/09/2022: Ch 5, Subfields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/11/2022: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/14/2022: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/16/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/18/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/21/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/23/2022: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/25/2022: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Midterm 1 covers Chs 1 through 8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/28/2022: Ch 9, Ideals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/02/2022: Ch 9, Principal Ideals and PIDs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 03/04/2022: Ring Homomorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 03/07/2022: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/09/2022: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 03/11/2022: Ch 11, Irreducible polynomials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Spring Break! Final Paper first look due&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 03/28/2022: Ch 12, Extension Fields as Vector Spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/30/2022: Ch 13, Automorphism that Fix a Field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/01/2022: Ch 14, Counting Automorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/04/2022: Ch 15, Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/06/2022: Ch 15, Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/08/2022: Ch 16, Permutation Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/11/2022: Ch 17, Group Homomorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/13/2022: Ch 18, Subgroups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Midterm 2 covers Chs 9 through 18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/15/2022: Ch 19, Generators of (Sub)Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/18/2022: Ch 20, Cosets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/20/2022: Ch 20-21, Cosets and Lagrange&amp;rsquo;s Theorem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/22/2022: Ch 23, Normal Subgroups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/25/2022: Ch 23, Quotient Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/27/2022: Ch 25, Galois Theory Revisited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/29/2022: Ch 26, Solvable Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 05/02/2022: Ch 26, Solvable Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 05/04/2022: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 05/06/2022: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 05/09/2022: Workshop on Final Papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Final Exam emphasizes Chs 19-28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
