<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>syllabus | Dr. Courtney R. Gibbons</title>
    <link>/tag/syllabus/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/syllabus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>syllabus</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/logo_hu59eb531666db2293e6941038440d3ac1_22599_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>syllabus</title>
      <link>/tag/syllabus/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 498 (Seminar): Mathematics in Social Context</title>
      <link>/post/math498/2022-math498/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/math498/2022-math498/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Spring 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-big-picture&#34;&gt;The Big Picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to examine issues of social, structural, and institutional hierarchies that intersect with mathematics and statistics. This year, the course will examine several big themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Belonging&lt;/strong&gt; – what is “mathematical identity” and where does it come from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Rights&lt;/strong&gt; – can mathematical literacy be viewed as a tool for advancing equity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Districting&lt;/strong&gt; – how does mathematics help us understand gerrymandering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; – in what ways do algorithms contribute to or fight against social stratification?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;educational-goals&#34;&gt;Educational Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to satisfying the Social, Structural, and Institutional Hierarchies (SSIH) requirement for the concentration in Mathematics and Statistics, this course addresses the following Educational Goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intellectual Curiosity and Flexibility&lt;/strong&gt; – examining fact, phenomena, and issues in-depth, and from a variety of perspectives, and having the courage to revise beliefs and outlooks in light of new evidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding of Cultural Diversity&lt;/strong&gt; – critically engaging with multiple cultural traditions and perspectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethical, Informed, and Engaged Citizenship&lt;/strong&gt; – developing an awareness of the challenges and responsibilities of local, national, and global citizenship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/strong&gt; – expressing oneself with clarity and eloquence, in both traditional and contemporary media, through writing and speaking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expectations-and-assignments&#34;&gt;Expectations and Assignments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To dig deeply into the main themes of the course, you will need to prepare in advance for each class, actively participate, and complete all of the assignments. This is reflected in the final grade composition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog Posts: 40%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participation: 30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final Poster: 30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-class-tasks-reading-watching-or-listening&#34;&gt;Pre-Class Tasks (Reading, Watching, or Listening)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete the relevant task (reading, watching, or listening) assigned for each class, think about it carefully, and outline some thoughts to share in our class discussion. The list of tasks can be found on the last page of this document and may be updated (in a timely manner!) as the semester progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your attendance and active participation is really important to the stability and success of our learning community! If you need to miss more classes, please fill out the Absence Request Form in advance (link available on Blackboard). Every student may miss one class; if you need to miss more than that, we need to talk. Undiscussed absences (besides the first freebie) will lower your participation grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;blog-posts&#34;&gt;Blog Posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our course blog is a (class-only) space for you to engage critically with the course materials. Writing the blog posts will help you and your classmates initiate and inform class discussions. They will also give you the opportunity to practice skills directly related to effective writing, such as conciseness, clarity, and vividness. You will contribute an original blog post five (5) times throughout the semester according to the schedule posted on Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each blog post should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify a specific concept/idea/argument from the assigned task (with reference);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;either demonstrate understanding of the concept at issue and express agreement or disagreement, giving reasons, OR connect it to previous ideas/discussions, or to contemporary issues, OR introduce an example/counter-example not explored in the text;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be more than be simply a summary or an unsupported opinion (“I liked this reading”);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end with a potential question or topic for class discussion, related to your post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each blog post should be between 150 and 250 words. You must post your contribution by 7pm the day before our class meeting. I will grade each post according to the rubric posted on Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-poster&#34;&gt;Final Poster&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a capstone assignment, you will create a poster to explore a topic of your choice. This poster will be due after spring break, and we will convene for one more class session to present the class posters to the Math and Stats department.  You must submit a brief outline (bullet points are fine) of the content of your poster by the last day of the course. A pdf of your final poster is the third Tuesday after spring break, and you should submit your request to print the poster to LITS on this date as well. The poster should be well organized with clear exposition and proper citations. Please see &lt;a href=&#34;https://libguides.hamilton.edu/c.php?g=749942&amp;amp;p=5370642&#34;&gt;https://libguides.hamilton.edu/c.php?g=749942&amp;amp;p=5370642&lt;/a&gt; for more information about the technical aspects of creating a poster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;required-books&#34;&gt;Required Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations: Civil Rights from Mississippi to the Algebra Project (Beacon Press, 2001)
NOTE: ebook available with Hamilton College login
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hamilton.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01HAMILTON_INST/15ojthq/alma9917657883304131&#34;&gt;https://hamilton.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01HAMILTON_INST/15ojthq/alma9917657883304131&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor-code&#34;&gt;Honor Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your blog posts and final poster must consist primarily of your own individual work and include citations for works that you are responding to or works that informed your thinking (this includes formal works, websites, videos, or other sources). You and I are also bound by the Hamilton Honor Code to report instances of plagiarism or other academic dishonesty that we become aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accessibility&#34;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students who require academic accommodations should contact the Dean of Students Office to coordinate services. Talk to me to ensure that your needs will be met this semester, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading-and-discussion-schedule&#34;&gt;Reading and Discussion Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-1---belonging&#34;&gt;Week 1 - Belonging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introductions, Classroom Conversations, and Mathematics Identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-2-and-3---civil-rights&#34;&gt;Weeks 2 and 3 - Civil Rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Andrew Hacker, Is Algebra Really Necessary?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Radical Equations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations, Chapters 1 and 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Radical Equations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Robert P. Moses ‘56, Radical Equations, Chapters 3 and 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - College Rankings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-4-5-and-6---political-districting&#34;&gt;Weeks 4, 5, and 6 - Political Districting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Gerrymandering Overview&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: David Wasserman, “Hating Gerrymandering is Easy: Fixing it is Harder” FiveThirtyEight, The Gerrymandering Project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read:  Nick Corasanti et al., “How Maps Reshape American Politics”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Efficiency Gap&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Mira Bernstein and Moon Duchin, A Formula Goes to Court: Partisan Gerrymandering and the Efficiency Gap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Monte Carlo Markov Chains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday- Supreme Court&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Elena Kagan, Opinion and Dissent in Gerrymandering Case, June 27, 2019
&lt;em&gt;This document is 72 pages long; allow 2 - 3 hours reading time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, Trial by Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Laurence Tribe, Trial by Mathematics: Precision and Ritual in the Legal Process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weeks-6-and-7---algorithms&#34;&gt;Weeks 6 and 7 - Algorithms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Cathy O’Neill, Weapons of Math Destruction, Intro &amp;amp; Chapters 1, 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Ethical Applications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch: Youtube Playlist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday - The Ethics Matrix&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: Cathy O’Neil and Hanna Gunn, “The Ethical Matrix” [Introduction, Sections 8.4-8.7]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-8---belonging-revisited&#34;&gt;Week 8 - Belonging Revisited&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday - Belonging Revisited&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read: “STEM Identity Development in Latinas: The Role of Self- and Outside Recognition” [Section - Literature Review (pp. 2-3); Section - Implications for Policy and Practice (pp. 16-17)]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen: My Favorite Theorem podcast interview with Ranthony Edmonds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday- Course Conclusions&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math 325 (Writing Intensive): Modern Algebra</title>
      <link>/post/syllabi/2022-math325/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/syllabi/2022-math325/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revised Spring 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-word-algebra&#34;&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;Algebra&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and its mathematical connotation stem from a 9th century
Arabic treatise entitled, &lt;em&gt;The Concise Book on Calculation by Restoration and Compensation&lt;/em&gt;, by al-Kwarizmi. This historical text dealt with finding the roots of a general quadratic polynomial equation, $ax^2+bx+c=0$ for nonzero $a$, by completing the square&amp;mdash;hence &amp;ldquo;restoration&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;compensation.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; This is where our journey begins. By the end of the course, we&amp;rsquo;ll have an understanding of what tools and techniques &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; (19th and 20th century) algebra brings to bear on polynomials and their roots. This course gets more abstract as the semester progresses, so set good habits early. (See Endotes 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texts&#34;&gt;Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract Algebra: A Concrete Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Redfield (available from the Hamilton College Bookstore; see me if you have difficulty acquiring the book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Princeton Companion to Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Bowers-Green, Leader, and Gowers (access the ebook via the Hamilton College library with your Hamilton SSO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the 
&lt;a href=&#34;/files/syllabi/325-S2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Topics Schedule Table (tentative)&lt;/a&gt; or the list at the end of the page for the day-to-day topics coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-and-practices&#34;&gt;Skills and Practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Intensive:&lt;/strong&gt; We will focus on writing during class, and you will have several revision opportunities on writing assignments and the writing portions of exams. The final paper in the course will allow you to tie together what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned (and what you&amp;rsquo;ve already written in earlier writing assignments) into a mathematical survey paper written for a mathematically literate audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support your progress as a writer of mathematics, I can help you during open hours or on Piazza, and the QSR Center and the Writing Center both have a number of peer tutors who are familiar with mathematical proof writing and $\LaTeX$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; This course supports several of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hamilton.edu/academics/catalogue/educational-goals-and-curriculum/educational-goals&#34; title=&#34;Hamilton&amp;#39;s Educational Goals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s Educational Goals&lt;/a&gt;. Much of the &lt;em&gt;Disciplinary Practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Communication and Expression&lt;/em&gt; within mathematics comes through the process of solving a problem/proving a proposition and then writing it up. In this class, you will refine your proof writing skills and develop new mathematical prose writing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-assessments&#34;&gt;Types of Assessments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ready for Class (RC)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Beginning of Class&lt;/em&gt;. We we are working toward answering one (huge!) mathematical problem; you will find it really helpful to review your notes and preview the book for these short quiz-like multiple choice assignments. I don’t reschedule these, but I do drop (at least) three low scores for everyone. (We can work out COVID contingencies as necessary!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework (HW)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Tuesdays at 4pm (rigid)&lt;/em&gt;. The homework is graded by a Hamilton student and will be returned in 2-3 class periods. Because the written homework is graded by a student who is super-busy just like you, homework is due when it&amp;rsquo;s due! (Don&amp;rsquo;t @ me!) However, to help you out, I drop your lowest 2 homework scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Midterm Exams (ME)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Two 2-hour self-scheduled midterms&lt;/em&gt;. Before the first exam, I will post a preview that describes the kinds of questions, the point distributions, and other information that will help you study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Exam (FE)&lt;/strong&gt;: One 3-hour cumulative self-scheduled exam. The material on the final, though cumulative, will be weighted toward the material covered at the end of the course that was not tested on midterms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Assignments (WA)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due Thursdays at 4pm (flexible)&lt;/em&gt;. You will write up solutions to problems and responses to writing prompts roughly once a week using $\LaTeX$ (via 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; with your Hamilton SSO) (sometimes solo, sometimes in partners). Each writing assignment is graded among the options &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; (exemplary), &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; (masterful), &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; (consider revising), and &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; (not enough to assess).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Paper (FP)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Due by beginning of our scheduled final exam period&lt;/em&gt;. This will be graded like a writing assignment; a lot of the content of this paper will come from writing assignments you&amp;rsquo;ve already completed, so think of it as a way to study for the final and get a chance to revise your writing one last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classroom-environment&#34;&gt;Classroom Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Mathematical Society (the largest professional society for mathematicians) outlines its vision for a welcoming environment as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMS strives to ensure that participants in its activities enjoy a welcoming environment. In all its activities, the AMS seeks to foster an atmosphere that encourages the free expression and exchange of ideas. The AMS supports equality of opportunity and treatment for all participants, regardless of gender, gender identity or expression, race, color, national or ethnic origin, religion or religious belief, age, marital status, sexual orientation, disabilities, veteran status, or immigration status&amp;hellip;. A commitment to a welcoming environment is expected of all attendees at AMS activities, including mathematicians, students, guests, staff, contractors and exhibitors, and participants in scientific sessions and social events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am committed to the same vision for our classroom environment, and I sincerely thank you for your contributions toward making our classroom (and office hours) a lively and respectful community of thinkers. Please let me know if you feel that we have strayed from this vision at any point during the semester. (See Endnotes 2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-responsibilities&#34;&gt;Your Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piazza&lt;/strong&gt; This term we will be using Piazza for online discussions (and virtual office hours). The system is highly catered to getting you help fast and efficiently from classmates, the course grader, and me. Rather than emailing questions to the me, please post your questions on Piazza, and I will try to keep a record of office hours questions on Piazza, too. If you have any problems or feedback for the developers, email &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:team@piazza.com&#34;&gt;team@piazza.com&lt;/a&gt;. You can access Piazza directly through Blackboard by cliclking &amp;ldquo;Piazza&amp;rdquo; in the course menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accommodations, Conflicts, &amp;amp; Makeup Exams&lt;/strong&gt; Please give me notice at least one week prior to an that you have an academic accommodation or a conflict. Since the exams in this course are self-scheduled, I hope this allows you the flexibility to plan around your other obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy to work with you if you need additional flexibility. T&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendance &amp;amp; Honor&lt;/strong&gt; By enrolling in this class, you are agreeing to be an engaged student, to come to class with a learner&amp;rsquo;s attitude, and to encourage your fellow students to do the same. If you need to miss a class, please fill out the Class Absence Request Form (link available on Blackboard). You are part of a community that believes in the power of the Honor Code to make Hamilton College a great place to be a student and a teacher. We are all bound by the responsibility to actively create and maintain a culture of learning, academic integrity, and personal honor. I do not take my responsibility lightly; nor should you! (See Endnotes 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Stuck&lt;/strong&gt; Being stumped is part of learning mathematics, so please attempt to solve homework problems on your own before asking for help on them. Collaboration on the homework is encouraged as long as you are collaborating with your peers currently enrolled in any section of Math 325. However, make sure to write up your final drafts separately to ensure that you have each fully understood the answer(s). Similarly, even though you will be assigned a writing partner for the writing assignments, it is your responsibility to make sure you understand and approve of all the mathematics your team turns in. (See Endnotes 4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Please check with me before using resources other than your classmates, Piazza, tutors at the QSR or Writing Centers, or online $\LaTeX$ help. For example, check with me before asking other professors, students not currently enrolled in Math 325, the internet, a magic eight ball, the ghost of Gauss, etc! Mathematical plagiarism is a subtle business, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to accidentally plagiarize by copying a solution you&amp;rsquo;ve read somewhere else.&lt;/em&gt; (See Endnotes 5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Oxford English Dictionary, retrieve 01/ar/30, 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS Policy on a Welcoming Environment, retrieve 01/ar/30, 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you wantonly skip class, aside from missing out on the learning community within the walls of our classroom, you&amp;rsquo;ll penalize yourself by getting lower homework and test scores than you otherwise would. And anyway, I do notice if you&amp;rsquo;re not in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor Code issues aside, you&amp;rsquo;re doing yu02/uc/ion a disservice if you turn in work you have not personally thought through carefl02/Pl/, some Writing Assignment problems will reappear on exams or on the final paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, though: you can&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;unsee&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution. There are deep and interesting ethical conundra lurking here; Googling unwisely (or at all) may lead you down a path you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to  low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spring-2022-schedule-of-topics&#34;&gt;Spring 2022 Schedule of Topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 01/19/2022: Ch 1, Well-Ordering and Division&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 01/21/2022: Ch 1, Primes and GCDs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 01/24/2022: Ch 1, Induction,  FT of arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 01/26/2022: Ch 3, Complex Numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 01/28/2022: Ch 3, Complex Numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 01/31/2022: Ch 4, Modular Arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/02/2022: LaTeX Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/04/2022: Ch 4, Zero Divisors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/07/2022: Ch 5, Fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/09/2022: Ch 5, Subfields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/11/2022: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/14/2022: Ch 6, Solvability by Radicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/16/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/18/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/21/2022: Ch 7, Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 02/23/2022: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 02/25/2022: Ch 8, Polynomial Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Midterm 1 covers Chs 1 through 8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 02/28/2022: Ch 9, Ideals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/02/2022: Ch 9, Principal Ideals and PIDs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 03/04/2022: Ring Homomorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 03/07/2022: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/09/2022: Ch 10, Algebraic Elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 03/11/2022: Ch 11, Irreducible polynomials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Spring Break! Final Paper first look due&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 03/28/2022: Ch 12, Extension Fields as Vector Spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 03/30/2022: Ch 13, Automorphism that Fix a Field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/01/2022: Ch 14, Counting Automorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/04/2022: Ch 15, Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/06/2022: Ch 15, Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/08/2022: Ch 16, Permutation Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/11/2022: Ch 17, Group Homomorphisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/13/2022: Ch 18, Subgroups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Midterm 2 covers Chs 9 through 18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/15/2022: Ch 19, Generators of (Sub)Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/18/2022: Ch 20, Cosets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/20/2022: Ch 20-21, Cosets and Lagrange&amp;rsquo;s Theorem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/22/2022: Ch 23, Normal Subgroups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 04/25/2022: Ch 23, Quotient Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 04/27/2022: Ch 25, Galois Theory Revisited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 04/29/2022: Ch 26, Solvable Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 05/02/2022: Ch 26, Solvable Groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W 05/04/2022: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;F 05/06/2022: Ch 27-28, Putting it All Together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M 05/09/2022: Workshop on Final Papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Final Exam emphasizes Chs 19-28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
